D. C. Historic Preservation Division P002 P002
Stage
D. C. Historic Preservation Division Photograph Collection
1970-1987
Stage
P002
3 Linear Feet
Biographical / Historical
The D.C. Historic Preservation Division is part of the Department of Consumer and Regulatory Affairs and is governed by the D.C. Historic Landmark and Historic District Protection Act of 1978 (D.C. Law 2-144). In August, 1983, the Council established the D.C. Historic Preservation Review Board as an appointed D.C. advisory board with the Division serving as staff for the Board. Prior to the Board's creation, a Joint Committee established by the Commission of Fine Arts and the National Capital Planning Commission regularly prepared a list of Landmarks of the National Capital and designated properties for the National Register of Historic Places. The Division is now the agency responsible for surveying historic properties in D.C. in order to maintain the Inventory of Historic Sites, many of which are included in the National Register of Historic Places. The Division also reviews and issues building permits for properties of historic significance.
Custodial History
The photographs were donated to the Archives by Stephen Collcott for the Historic Preservation Division of the D.C. Government.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains three linear feet of photographs, negatives, and some slides, of historic properties in the City taken from approximately 1970-1987. The photographs consist of two types: snapshots and enlargements submitted by applicants to support their requests for building permits to renovate historic properties; and photographs maintained by the Division of historic buildings in the District. The collection also contains a very small amount of letters related to historic properties. Photographs of the Anacostia, Adams Morgan, Mount Pleasant, Capitol Hill, Ledroit Park, Logan Circle, Dupont Circle, Georgetown, and Downtown neighborhoods as well as buildings such as the Renwick Gallery of Art, Grace Episcopal Church, the National Cathedral School, and the Stoddart Baptist Home, among others, are in the collection.
In order to maintain the original order established by the Division, folders are arranged into three series: Neighborhoods, Geographical Quadrants, and Landmarks. Within these main divisions, folders are arranged alphabetically with general materials appearing before the more specific.
In 2014 preservation work on the collection resulted in some additional processing. All images were removed from improper housing and re-housed into new archival safe polyester sleeves. New folder titles were created in the same style/manor as the original order of the collection. This was done to provide a greater understanding of what street locations were contained within each series. For preservation reasons, larger formatted items were from folders and moved to a flat storage box (box 8). Duplicate prints, originally housed in box 8 were re-integrated into the collection.
Architecture; Photographs
- Series 1: Neighborhoods
  - Anacostia - General, ca. 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anacostia - Named and Lettered Streets - Chester Street, ca. 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anacostia - Named and Lettered Streets - Mapleview Place, ca. 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anacostia - Named and Lettered Streets - Martin Luther King Avenue, ca. 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anacostia - Named and Lettered Streets - Mount View Place, ca. 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anacostia - Named and Lettered Streets - Pleasant Street, ca. 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anacostia - Named and Lettered Streets - U Street, ca. 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anacostia - Named and Lettered Streets - V Street, ca. 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Anacostia - Named and Lettered Streets - Valley Place, ca. 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Anacostia - Named and Lettered Streets - W Street, ca. 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Anacostia - Numbered Streets - 14th Street, ca. 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Anacostia - Avondale Cooperative Apartments (ca. 1980), ca. 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Capitol Hill - General, 1976-1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Capitol Hill - Eastern Market, 1976-1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - A Street, 1976-1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - Acker Place, 1976-1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - Brown's Court, 1976-1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - C Street, 1976-1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - Constitution Avenue, 1976-1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - D Street, 1976-1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - E Street, 1976-1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - East Capitol Street, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - F Street, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - G Street, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - Independence Avenue, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - Kentucky Avenue, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - Lexington Place, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - Maryland Avenue, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - Massachusetts Avenue, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - North Carolina Avenue, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - O Street, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Capitol Hill - Named and Lettered Streets - Pennsylvania Avenue, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Capitol Hill - Numbered Streets - 1st Street, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Capitol Hill - Numbered Streets - 2nd Street, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Capitol Hill - Numbered Streets - 3rd Street, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Capitol Hill - Numbered Streets - 4th Street, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Capitol Hill - Numbered Streets - 7th Street, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Capitol Hill - Numbered Streets - 8th Street, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Capitol Hill - Numbered Streets - 9th Street, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Capitol Hill - Numbered Streets - 10th Street, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Capitol Hill - Numbered Streets - 11th Street, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Capitol Hill - Numbered Streets - 12th Street, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Cleveland Park, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Downtown - Named and Lettered Streets - E Street, 1901, 1917, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Downtown - Named and Lettered Streets - F Street, 1901, 1917, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Downtown - Named and Lettered Streets - G Street, 1901, 1917, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Downtown - Named and Lettered Streets - New York Avenue, 1901, 1917, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Downtown - Named and Lettered Streets - Pennsylvania Avenue, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Downtown - Numbered Streets - 6th Street, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Downtown - Numbered Streets - 7th Street *, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Downtown - Numbered Streets - 8th Street, 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Downtown - Numbered Streets - 9th Street, 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Downtown - Numbered Streets - 10th Street, 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Downtown - Numbered Streets - 11th Street, 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Downtown - Numbered Streets - 13th Street, 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Downtown - Numbered Streets - 15th Street, 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dupont Circle - General, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Dupont Circle - Named and Lettered Streets - Connecticut Avenue, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Dupont Circle - Named and Lettered Streets - Corcoran Street, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Dupont Circle - Named and Lettered Streets - Church Street, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Dupont Circle - Named and Lettered Streets - Dupont Circle, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Dupont Circle - Named and Lettered Streets - Florida Avenue, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Dupont Circle - Named and Lettered Streets - Hillyer Place, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Dupont Circle - Named and Lettered Streets - N Street, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Dupont Circle - Named and Lettered Streets - New Hampshire Avenue *, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Dupont Circle - Named and Lettered Streets - O Street, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Dupont Circle - Named and Lettered Streets - P Street, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Dupont Circle - Named and Lettered Streets - Q Street, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Dupont Circle - Named and Lettered Streets - Riggs Place, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Dupont Circle - Named and Lettered Streets - S Street *, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Dupont Circle - Named and Lettered Streets - Swann Street, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Dupont Circle - Numbered Streets - 17th Street, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Dupont Circle - Numbered Streets - 18th Street, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Dupont Circle - Numbered Streets-19th Street *, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Dupont Circle - Numbered Streets - 20th Street, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Dupont Circle - Numbered Streets - 21st Street, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Dupont Circle - Numbered Streets - 22nd Street, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Dupont Circle - Numbered Streets - Gallaudet College (1985), 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Georgetown - General * **, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Georgetown - Georgetown University, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - Bank Street, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - Canal Street, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - Dent Place, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - Dumbarton Street, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - Grace Street, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - K Street, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - M Street, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - N Street, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - O Street, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - P Street, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - Q Street, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - R Street *, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - Reservoir Road, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - Thomas Jefferson Street, 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - Water Street, 1978-1994 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Georgetown - Named and Lettered Streets - Wisconsin Avenue *, 1978-1994 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Georgetown - Numbered Streets - 28th Street, 1978-1994 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Georgetown - Numbered Streets - 30th Street, 1978-1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Georgetown - Numbered Streets - 31st Street *, 1978-1994 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Georgetown - Numbered Streets - 32nd Street **, 1978-1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Georgetown - Numbered Streets - 34th Street, 1978-1994 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Georgetown - Numbered Streets - 35th Street *, 1978-1994 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Oak Hill Cemetery *, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - LeDroit Park - Named and Lettered Streets - Elm Street, 1978-1981 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - LeDroit Park - Named and Lettered Streets - Florida Avenue, 1978-1981 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - LeDroit Park - Named and Lettered Streets - T Street, 1978-1981 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - LeDroit Park - Numbered Streets - 3rd Street, 1978-1981 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - LeDroit Park - Numbered Streets - 5th Street, 1978-1981 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Logan Circle - Bound Volume: "Number Seven Logan Circle", 1976-1980 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Logan Circle - Bound Volume: "Number Seven Logan Circle", 1976-1980 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Logan Circle - General, 1976-1980 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Logan Circle - Corcoran Street, 1976-1980 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Logan Circle - Rhode Island Avenue, 1976-1980 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Logan Circle - Vermont Avenue *, 1976-1980 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - The Maples, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Massachusetts Avenue - 2027 Massachusetts Avenue, 1981-1985 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Mount Pleasant - Named and Lettered Streets - Adams Mill Road, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Mount Pleasant - Named and Lettered Streets - Newton Street, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Mount Pleasant - Named and Lettered Streets - Park Road, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Mount Pleasant - Numbered Streets - 18th Street, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Schneider Triangle Square 38, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Takoma Park, ca. 1970 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Series 2: Geographic Quadrants
  - Northeast - Named and Lettered Streets - A Street, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Northeast - Named and Lettered Streets - C Street, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Northeast - Named and Lettered Streets - D Street, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Northeast - Named and Lettered Streets - E Street, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Northeast - Named and Lettered Streets - East Capitol, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Northeast - Named and Lettered Streets - F Street, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Northeast - Named and Lettered Streets - Massachusetts Avenue, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Northeast - Named and Lettered Streets - North Carolina Avenue, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Northeast - Numbered Streets - 7th Street, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Northeast - Numbered Streets - 8th Street, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Northeast - Numbered Streets - 11th Street, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Northeast - Numbered Streets - 14th Street, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - Cathedral Avenue, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - East Capitol, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - Grace Street, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - Highland Place, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - I Street, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - K Street, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - L Street, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - M Street *, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - N Street, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - O Street, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - P Street, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - Park Road, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - Pennsylvania Avenue, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - Prospect Street, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - Reservoir Road, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - Roadmen Street, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - U Street, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - Volta Place, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Northwest - Named and Lettered Streets - Wisconsin Avenue, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Northwest - Numbered Streets - 9th Street, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Northwest - Numbered Streets - 16th Street *, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Northwest - Numbered Streets-19th Street, 1970-1987 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Northwest - Numbered Streets - 29th Street, 1970-1987 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Northwest - Numbered Streets - 30th Street, 1970-1987 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Northwest - Numbered Streets - 31st Street, 1970-1987 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Northwest - Numbered Streets - 33rd Street, 1970-1987 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Northwest - Numbered Streets - 33rd Place, 1970-1987 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Northwest - Numbered Streets - 34th Street, 1970-1987 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Northwest - Numbered Streets - 35th Street, 1970-1987 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Northwest - Numbered Streets - 36th Street, 1970-1987 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Southeast - Named and Lettered Streets - A Street, 1980-1987 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Southeast - Named and Lettered Streets - E Street, 1980-1987 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Southeast - Named and Lettered Streets - East Capitol Street, 1980-1987 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Southeast - Named and Lettered Streets - G Street, 1980-1987 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Southeast - Named and Lettered Streets - Pennsylvania Avenue, 1980-1987 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Southeast - Numbered Streets - 6th Street, 1980-1987 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Southeast - Numbered Streets - 8th Street, 1980-1987 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Southeast - Numbered Streets - 9th Street, 1980-1987 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Southeast - Numbered Streets - 11th Street, 1980-1987 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Southeast - Numbered Streets - 12th Street, 1980-1987 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Southeast - Numbered Streets - 13th Street, 1980-1987 (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Series 3: Landmarks
  - Bacon House, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Bond Building, undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Carnegie Library, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Colorado Building, undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Grace Episcopal Church, undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Howard Theater, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Masonic Temple (National Museum of Women in the Arts), undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - National Bank of Washington, undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - National Cathedral School, undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Renwick Gallery of Art **, undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Riggs Bank, undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - St. Albans School, undated (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Tivoli Theater, undated (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - USS Williamsburg, undated (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Warner Theater, undated (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Washington National Cathedral, undated (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Western Union Building, undated (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Woodward and Lothrup Building, undated (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Unidentified Materials, undated (Box 7, Folder 39)